Guide to the UE Local 107 Records, 1933-1987 UE.16.107
ULS Archives & Special Collections
UE Local 107 Records
1933-1987
ULS Archives & Special Collections
United Electrical, Radio and Machine Workers of America. Local 107 (Essington, Pa.)
UE.16.107
35 Linear Feet (28 boxes)
Operating from 1936 to 1986 at the South Philadelphia Works of the Westinghouse Company in Lester, Pennsylvania and Essington, Pennsylvania, United Electrical, Radio and Machine Workers of America (UE) Local 107 represented workers in collective bargaining and sought the adjustment of grievances originating in contract and shop floor disputes. The bulk of the materials date from 1942 to 1987 and include correspondence, meeting minutes, publications, grievances, legal files, newspaper clippings, and subject files.
History
Initially, workers at the Lester plant chartered Local 107 under the American Federation of Labor. In 1936, Local 107 withdrew from AFL and affiliated with the newly created Congress of Industrial Organization(CIO). In November, the Lester workers voted to join a group of independent locals in the United Electrical, Radio and Machine Workers of America(UE).
In 1946, Local 107 succeeded in obtaining a $1 per hour increase in wages after organizing a four month strike. During the strike, children joined their parents on the picket lines and the company countered by securing court injunctions against mass picketing.
In 1948, two members of Local 107 were labeled as a "poor security risk" by the Navy. Based upon these accusations, the Westinghouse Company forced the two men to take an unpaid leave of absence until they could be cleared of the charges. The local responded with a work stoppage which convinced the company to reinstate the workers.
Throughout the early 1950s, Local 107 was raided by several unions, but successfully maintained its position in the South Philadelphia Works. The International Union of Electrical Workers (IUE), Patternmakers Union, and the International Association of Machinists all competed with Local 107 to represent workers in the South Philadelphia area plants.
In 1954, despite a vigorous campaign by Local 107, Westinghouse Electric relocated its Aviation Gas Turbine Division from the South Philadelphia area to Kansas City. This loss was followed by another in 1955, when the company decided to cancel all agreements with the local and push for a 20 percent wage cut. The threatened wage cut brought about a strike that lasted 299 days. In the midst of the strike, 26 union officers and members chose to spend 19 days in jail, rather than pay $27,000 in fines.
In 1960, Local 107 dedicated a new union hall, and 1962 marked the first year of the annual retiree banquets. Nonetheless, the 1960s and 1970s proved to be rather turbulent decades. In 1966, the local supported two strikes and approximately eight walkouts. Another strike occurred in 1969. Beginning in August 1970, Local 107 went on a 146 day strike to obtain higher job rates. In July 1976, the union participated in a nation-wide strike that lasted five days.
In order to facilitate contract negotiations and secure better conditions, the UE, IUE, and IBEW began coordinating their negotiations. The increased leverage at the bargaining table did not stop subcontracting and runaway shops, and, in 1977, the local responded by filing a brief with the National Labor Relations Board(NLRB), which sought to stop the practice of subcontracting without prior notification. Notwithstanding these efforts, the Lester workforce continued to diminish, and in December 1986, the Lester plant finally closed. Local 107 continued to operate on a limited basis for an additional year to assist displaced workers and retirees.
Scope and Content Notes
This subgroup contains documents created or collected by UE Local 107 at Westinghouse plants in Lester and Essington, Pennsylvania, from 1933 to 1987. Included are materials concerning the function of the local, such as by-laws, financial records, publications, and minutes. Also present are records regarding work in the plant. These include grievances, job descriptions, and contracts between the local and Westinghouse. Newspaper clippings, correspondence, subject files, and legal files provide background on labor issues on the national and local levels. Photographs depict Local 107 members participating in lockouts, strikes, meetings, and other union events.
Arrangement
Series 16.107.1. Constitution and Bylaws, 1946-1985
Series 16.107.2. Contract Files, 1943-1986
Series 16.107.3. Correspondence, 1943-1987
Series 16.107.4. Financial Records, 1944-1980
Series 16.107.5. Grievances, 1942-1986
Series 16.107.6. Legal Files, 1942-1985
Series 16.107.7. Minutes, 1933-1986
Series 16.107.8. Newspaper Clippings, 1955-1971
Series 16.107.9. Publications, 1948-1985
Series 16.107.10. Rate Ranges and Job Descriptions, 1941-1986
Series 16.107.11. Subject Files, 1940-1986
Series 16.107.12. Photographs
Series 16.107.13. Oversize Materials
Access Restrictions
Access to the records of the United Electrical, Radio, and Machine Workers of America are closed for a period of twenty-five years after their creation. Access to individual legal case files and correspondence regarding discharges and discipline requires a signed confidentiality agreement.
Acquisition Information
Gift of United Electrical, Radio and Machine Workers of America Local 107 in 1988.
Previous Citation
UE Local 107 Records, 1933-1987, UE.16.107, Archives Service Center, University of Pittsburgh
United Electrical, Radio and Machine Workers of America (UE) Local 107 Records, 1933-1987, UE:LOCAL107, Archives Service Center, University Library System, University of Pittsburgh
Related Material
UE National Office Records Relating to District 1 and District 1 Locals, 1936-1990s, UE.4.1.1, Archives & Special Collections, University of Pittsburgh Library System
UE District 1 Records, 1950s-1986, UE.15.1, Archives & Special Collections, University of Pittsburgh Library System
UE News Photograph Collection, 1933-1998, UE.14.1, Archives & Special Collections, University of Pittsburgh Library System
Electric industry workers -- Labor unions -- Pennsylvania -- History; Labor; Philadelphia (Pa.); Lester (Pa.); Essington (Pa.); Labor unions -- Organizing -- United States; Labor unions -- United States -- History -- 20th century; United Electrical, Radio and Machine Workers of America -- History; United Electrical, Radio and Machine Workers of America. Local 107 (Essington, Pa.); Westinghouse Electric Corporation. Aviation Gas Turbine Division; Westinghouse Electric Corporation. Marine Division; Westinghouse Electric Corporation. Steam Division; Westinghouse Electric Corporation; Glavin, Dennis; Price, James
- Constitution and Bylaws, 1946-1985; 16.107.1.
  Scope and Contents note
  Dating from 1946 to 1985, this series contains the constitution and bylaws for Local 107, as well as the yearly amendments.
  - Constitution and Bylaws, 1946-1959 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Constitutional Amendments, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Constitutional Amendments, 1967-1985 (Box 1, Folder 3-5)
- Contracts and Negotiations, 1943-1986; 16.107.2.
  This series is separated into two groups: contract materials between Westinghouse Electric Company and Local 107, and supplemental agreements between Westinghouse Electric Company and other UE locals. The Local 107 files are arranged chronologically and contain major contract agreements, supplemental agreements, data collected for negotiations, and union proposals, which focus on issues such as wage increases, job rates, pensions and benefit plans.
  - Contract Materials, 1943-1986 (Box 1, Folder 6-19)
  - Contract of Westinghouse Salaried Employees, 1950-1966 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Local Contract Supplements - District 1, 1946-1950 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Local Contract Supplements - District 2-3, 1947-1949 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Local Contract Supplements - District 4, 1946-1959 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Local Contract Supplements - District 6, 1946-1951 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Local Contract Supplements - District 7, 1946-1947 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Local Contract Supplements - Miscellaneous, 1946-1952 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Correspondence, 1943-1987; 16.107.3.
  The correspondence files are arranged by correspondent or topic. Several files contain correspondence between Local 107 and Westinghouse Electric, which cover discharges, disciplinary actions, leaves of absence, and other employment issues. The UE District One files contain notifications for meetings and conventions, as well as general information on negotiations and other union business.
  - Aviation Gas Turbine Division, 1953-1954 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Company Letters, 1976-1983 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Delaware County Industrial Council, 1949-1952 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Discharges, 1957-1984 (Box 2, Folder 10-12)
  - Disciplinary Cases, 1957-1969 (Box 2, Folder 13-14)
  - District One (UE), 1974-1987 (Box 2, Folder 15-19)
  - Financial, 1943-1949 (Box 2, Folder 20-23)
  - Industrial Relations, 1962-1984 (Box 3, Folder 1-2)
  - Leave of Absence, 1963-1982 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Legal, 1957-1985 (Box 3, Folder 4-5)
  - Legislative Committee, 1957-1966 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Miscellaneous, 1947-1987 (Box 3, Folder 7-16)
  - Tomasetti, Nicholas, 1972-1977 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Union Statements, 1960-1963 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Wage Stabilization Board, 1952 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Works Engineering, 1943-1962 (Box 3, Folder 20)
- Financial Records, 1944-1980; 16.107.4.
  This series consists of audits, monthly financial statements, ledgers, and steward expenditures for Local 107, arranged by record type. This series also contains a folder of financial reports from UE District One.
  - Audit, 1956-1972 (Box 3, Folder 21-22)
  - Ledger, 1946-1951 (Box 4, Folder 1-2)
  - Monthly Financial Statements, 1944-1980 (Box 4, Folder 3-15)
  - Steward Expenditures, 1953-1980 (Box 4, Folder 16-23)
  - UE District One - Financial Statements, 1958-1969 (Box 4, Folder 24)
- Grievances, 1942-1986; 16.107.5.
  The grievance files are separated into two groups: grievance correspondence and grievance forms. The grievance correspondence is separated into company correspondence, which contains the company's answers to union grievances; and union correspondence, which states whether the company's response was satisfactory to the union or not. The grievance forms reveal the date, department and nature of the grievance. Several of the grievance form files also contain company responses and note whether the issue was settled, moved to the next step of the grievance procedure, or cause for strike action.
  - Correspondence - Company, 1942-1953 (Box 5, Folder 1-18)
  - Correspondence - Union - Fourth Level, 1970-1982 (Box 5, Folder 19-22)
  - Correspondence - Union - General, 1957-1985 (Box 6, Folder 1-18)
  - Correspondence - Union - Inactive, 1944-1951 (Box 6, Folder 19-22)
  - Forms - Aviation Gas Turbine Division, 1946-1955 (Box 7, Folder 1-3)
  - Forms - Balcony Department, 1958-1986 (Box 7, Folder 4-14)
  - Forms - Blade and Tool Department, 1955-1969 (Box 7, Folder 15-26)
  - Forms - Blade and Tool Department, 1971-1986 (Box 8, Folder 1-2)
  - Forms - Control Shop, 1962-1984 (Box 8, Folder 3-6)
  - Forms - D and BD Division, 1958-1986 (Box 8, Folder 7-13)
  - Forms - Erecting, 1955-1984 (Box 8, Folder 14-21)
  - Forms - General, 1954-1986 (Box 9, Folder 1-20)
  - Forms - Heavy Machine, 1961-1986 (Box 10, Folder 1-9)
  - Forms - Inconsistent Time Values, 1947 (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - Forms - National Appeal Grievance, 1958-1959 (Box 10, Folder 11-13)
  - Forms - Production Department, 1958-1961 (Box 10, Folder 14-16)
  - Forms - Retirement, 1947-1949 (Box 10, Folder 17)
  - Forms - Rocket Division, 1963-1965 (Box 10, Folder 18)
  - Forms - Salary, 1957-1960 (Box 10, Folder 19-20)
  - Forms - Small Steam and Gas Turbine, 1958-1960 (Box 10, Folder 21-23)
  - Forms - Small Steam and Gas Turbine, 1961-1985 (Box 11, Folder 1-8)
  - Forms - Steward Copy, 1950s-1980s (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - Forms - Steward Copy, 1950s-1980s (Box 12, Folder 1-3)
  - Forms - Strike Action, 1957-1967 (Box 13, Folder 1-8)
  - Forms - Transport and Stores, 1958-1986 (Box 13, Folder 9-20)
  - Forms - Works Engineering Department, 1956-1986 (Box 14, Folder 1-10)
  - Forms - Y Building, 1955-1969 (Box 14, Folder 11-19)
- Legal Files, 1942-1985; 16.107.6.
  Access Restrictions
  Access to individual case files requires a signed confidentiality agreement.
  Scope and Contents Notes
  Topics represented in this series include the arbitration of grievances, equal employment issues, and strike litigation. The National Labor Relations Board and War Labor Board files focus on contract negotiations and representation elections.
  - Arbitrations, 1942-1985 (Box 15, Folder 1-22)
  - Equal Employment Opportunity - Class Action, 1976-1981 (Box 15, Folder 23-24)
  - Equal Employment Opportunity - General, 1967-1979 (Box 15, Folder 25-26)
  - Equal Employment Opportunity - General, 1980-1985 (Box 16, Folder 1-3)
  - National Labor Relations Board - Certifications, 1941-1952 (Box 16, Folder 4)
  - NLRB - Charges Against Local 107, 1976-1977 (Box 16, Folder 5)
  - National Labor Relations Board - Concordville, 1980 (Box 16, Folder 6)
  - National Labor Relations Board - Miscellaneous, 1949-1980 (Box 16, Folder 7-10)
  - NLRB- Non Communist Affidavits, 1949-1959 (Box 16, Folder 11-13)
  - National Labor Relations Board - Salary, 1952, 1960 (Box 16, Folder 14-15)
  - National Labor Relations Board - Subcontracting, 1977-1978 (Box 16, Folder 16)
  - NLRB -Worker Adjustment Assistance, 1985 (Box 16, Folder 17)
  - National Labor Relations Board - Zieler Case, 1954 (Box 16, Folder 18)
  - Strike Related LitigatioN, 1955-1978 (Box 16, Folder 19-23)
  - War Labor Board - Broaches, 1944 (Box 16, Folder 24)
  - War Labor Board - Correspondence, 1943-1945 (Box 16, Folder 25-26)
  - War Labor Board - Miscellaneous, 1943-1944 (Box 16, Folder 27)
- Minutes, 1933-1986; 16.107.7.
  These files are separated into Executive Board, General Membership, Miscellaneous Minutes, and Roll Call. The executive board minutes date from 1946 to 1986 and contain reports from committees, the business agent, and financial secretary or treasurer. The minutes also provide information on events scheduled by the local, as well as brief descriptions of contract negotiations, major grievances, and communications from other UE locals and outside organizations. The general membership minutes date from 1947 to 1986 and duplicate much of the information from the executive board minutes. The roll call files date from 1933 to 1986 and list the attendance of Local 107 officers at executive board and general membership meetings.
  - Executive Board, 1946-1986 (Box 17, Folder 1-25)
  - General Membership, 1947-1986 (Box 18, Folder 1-22)
  - Relief Advisory Committee, 1948-1949 (Box 18, Folder 23)
  - Salary, 1952-1957 (Box 18, Folder 24)
  - Stewards, 1949-1985 (Box 18, Folder 25)
  - Roll Call, 1933-1986 (Box 18, Folder 26-28)
- Newspaper Clippings, 1955-1971; 16.107.8.
  This series provides detailed accounts of contract negotiations and strikes. This series is an especially strong source of information on the 1955-1956 strike and the accompanying arrest of union leaders. The clippings are generally from Philadelphia based news organs with some articles from The Wall Street Journal.
  - Newspaper Clippings - Miscellaneous, 1959-1971 (Box 19, Folder 1-2)
  - Newspaper Clippings - Strike, 1955-1970 (Box 19, Folder 3-8)
- Publications, 1948-1985; 16.107.9.
  This series contains bulletins, newsletters, notices and pamphlets created by Local 107 from 1948 to 1985. The bulletins and notices focus on specific events such as elections, strikes and meetings. The newsletters describe contract negotiations, candidates for elections, committee activities and developments at the Westinghouse Electric Company. In addition to the Local 107 based publications, this series contains publications from the Congress of Industrial Organizations, UE National and Westinghouse Electric Company.
  - Local 107 - Bulletins, 1948-1969 (Box 19, Folder 9-23)
  - Local 107 - Bulletins, 1970-1985 (Box 20, Folder 1-8)
  - Local 107 - Newsletter, 1952-1981 (Box 20, Folder 9-23)
  - Local 107 - Notices, 1976-1986 (Box 20, Folder 24-28)
  - Local 107 - Pamphlets, 1947-1960s (Box 20, Folder 29)
  - Congress of Industrial Organizations, 1945-1949 (Box 21, Folder 1)
  - Government, 1947-1960 (Box 21, Folder 2-3)
  - Labor Report, 1959-1962 (Box 21, Folder 4)
  - United Auto Workers, 1949 (Box 21, Folder 5)
  - United Electrical Workers - Local 124, 1958 (Box 21, Folder 6)
  - United Electrical Workers - National, 1946-1949 (Box 21, Folder 7)
  - Westinghouse - Bulletin, 1974-1986 (Box 21, Folder 8-9)
  - Westinghouse - Journal, 1975-1976 (Box 21, Folder 10)
  - Westinghouse - Miscellaneous, 1959-1976 (Box 21, Folder 11)
  - Westinghouse - Powerlines, 1977-1979 (Box 21, Folder 12-13)
- Rate Ranges and Job Descriptions, 1941-1986; 16.107.10.
  Job descriptions were used for the salary negotiations and the rate/wage ranges show the graduations of pay for each position depending on rank. These records are arranged first by shop and then by type.
  - Crane Operators, 1942-1967 (Box 21, Folder 14)
  - Control Shop, 1962-1966 (Box 21, Folder 15)
  - D Building, 1943-1960 (Box 21, Folder 16)
  - Erecting, 1943-1959 (Box 21, Folder 17)
  - General, 1942-1970 (Box 21, Folder 18-23)
  - Heavy Manufacturing, 1945-1967 (Box 21, Folder 24)
  - Light Shop, 1943-1961 (Box 21, Folder 25)
  - Tool and Die, 1942-1954 (Box 21, Folder 26)
  - Y Lab, 1954-1956 (Box 21, Folder 27)
  - Hourly Seniority Progression Charts, undated (Box 22, Folder 1-2)
  - Job Evaluations, 1942-1961 (Box 22, Folder 3)
  - Keysheets, 1941-1986 (Box 22, Folder 4)
  - Negotiations, 1951-1956, 1971 (Box 22, Folder 5-6)
  - Salary Classifications, undated (Box 22, Folder 7-8)
  - Shop Steward Rates, 1963-1981 (Box 22, Folder 9-13)
- Subject Files, 1940-1986; 16.107.11.
  This series covers a variety of research topics such as conventions, insurance and strikes. This series also contains several files on Local 107 committees, which organized activities such as athletic events, elections, dances, banquets, and Christmas parties for the members and their families. These files consist of correspondence, publications, leaflets and other materials.
  - Athletic Committee, 1959-1981 (Box 23, Folder 1)
  - Cafeteria Representation, 1947-1980 (Box 23, Folder 2-4)
  - Check Off, 1946-1980 (Box 23, Folder 5)
  - Cost of Living Adjustments, 1959-1960 (Box 23, Folder 6)
  - Donations, 1970-1986 (Box 23, Folder 7)
  - Education Committee, 1949-1980 (Box 23, Folder 8-9)
  - Election Committee, 1963-1984 (Box 23, Folder 10-12)
  - Entertainment Committee, 1944-1985 (Box 23, Folder 13-16)
  - Executive Committee, 1945-1985 (Box 23, Folder 17)
  - Fair Employment Practices Committee, 1963-1981 (Box 23, Folder 18)
  - Foreign Trade, 1971-1972 (Box 23, Folder 19)
  - Four Day Week, 1949-1955 (Box 23, Folder 20)
  - Grievance Procedure, 1949-1958 (Box 24, Folder 1)
  - Group Leaders, 1944-1947 (Box 24, Folder 2)
  - Human Resources Development Institute, 1969-1975 (Box 24, Folder 3-4)
  - Insurance, 1955-1977 (Box 24, Folder 5-6)
  - International Convention, 1944-1957 (Box 24, Folder 7-9)
  - Loans, 1958-1959 (Box 24, Folder 10)
  - Long Term Disability, 1972 (Box 24, Folder 11)
  - Lunch Hour Meetings, 1960-1961 (Box 24, Folder 12)
  - Main Office Supplies, 1941 (Box 24, Folder 13)
  - Measured Day Work, 1956-1960 (Box 24, Folder 14)
  - Medical, 1961-1985 (Box 24, Folder 15)
  - Medicare, 1967 (Box 24, Folder 16)
  - Membership Authorization, 1947-1949 (Box 24, Folder 17)
  - Membership Mailings, 1964-1971 (Box 24, Folder 18)
  - Miners Day Committee, 1950 (Box 24, Folder 19)
  - Miscellaneous Committees, 1948-1980 (Box 24, Folder 20)
  - Newspaper Committee, 1947-1969 (Box 24, Folder 21)
  - Non-Member Seniority Lists, 1958-1964 (Box 24, Folder 22)
  - Overtime Pay, 1942-1961 (Box 24, Folder 23)
  - Pennsylvania Industrial Council, 1947-1949 (Box 24, Folder 24)
  - Petitions, 1950s-1960s (Box 24, Folder 25)
  - Philadelphia Wage Tax, 1944-1949 (Box 24, Folder 26)
  - Plant Reorganization, 1959 (Box 24, Folder 27)
  - Poll Tax, 1942-1946 (Box 24, Folder 28)
  - Protest Demonstration, 1950 (Box 24, Folder 29)
  - Publicity, 1954-1955 (Box 24, Folder 30)
  - Red Circle, 1957-1964 (Box 24, Folder 31)
  - Resolutions, 1940-1952 (Box 24, Folder 32)
  - Retirees Banquets, 1962-1973 (Box 24, Folder 33)
  - Safety Committee, 1950 (Box 25, Folder 1)
  - Save Our Plant Committee, 1984 (Box 25, Folder 2)
  - Seniority and Layoff Procedures, 1944-1961 (Box 25, Folder 3)
  - Service Work, 1944-1952 (Box 25, Folder 4)
  - Shop Steward Appointments, 1977-1978 (Box 25, Folder 5)
  - Shop Steward Classes, 1944-1954 (Box 25, Folder 6)
  - Shop Steward Divisional Meetings, 1968 (Box 25, Folder 7)
  - Shop Steward General, 1960-1970 (Box 25, Folder 8)
  - Smith Act, 1952 (Box 25, Folder 9)
  - Strikes, 1946-1979 (Box 25, Folder 10-17)
  - Subcontracting, 1981-1983 (Box 25, Folder 18)
  - Taxes, 1945-1948 (Box 25, Folder 19)
  - Taft Hartley, 1947-1949 (Box 25, Folder 20)
  - Television Cameras, 1981 (Box 25, Folder 21)
  - Time Values, 1943-1948 (Box 25, Folder 22)
  - Training and Scholarship Committee, 1969-1976 (Box 25, Folder 23)
  - Training, 1951-1981 (Box 25, Folder 24-25)
  - Trak-Rak, 1961 (Box 25, Folder 26)
  - Unemployment Compensation, 1977-1978 (Box 25, Folder 27)
  - Wage Freeze, 1971 (Box 25, Folder 28)
  - Welders, 1942-1974 (Box 25, Folder 29)
  - Works Engineering, 1965-1975 (Box 25, Folder 30)
  - Westinghouse Electric and UE Local 107, undated (Box 26)
- Photographs, 1940-1986; 16.107.12.
  This series contains photographic prints and negatives of Local 107 events. Included are photographs of local strikes, lockouts, meetings, and members. Many of the photographs have not been identified.
  - Photographs, undated (Box 27-28)
- Oversize Materials, 16.107.13
  Scope and Content Notes
  This material was added to the finding aid in January 2011.
  - John Schaeffer Obituary, 1. (Map-case 10, Drawer 1)
  - Charter for Local 107 Retirees Association by the National Council of Senior Citizens, 1979; 2.